# Alec Hoyland

I'm a computational scientist at Clarifai and a PhD student in Biomedical Engineering at Worcester Polytechnic Institute. At Clarifai, I am a technical lead on a multi-million dollar ARR government R&D project, where my team designs and tests better object detection and tracking deep learning algorithms. My work contributed to a 35% improvement for some classes. For my PhD, I use advanced signal processing and machine learning to improve biosignal data collection and analysis, using 90% fewer samples for the same accuracy. My research interests include autoencoders, object detection, parameter optimization, signal processing, and neuroprosthetics.

#### Personal Data

LOCATION: Worcester, MA PHONE: 774-372-1164

Email: entropy/senergy@posteo.de | Website: https://github.com/alec-hoyland

### TECHNICAL DETAILS

Programming Languages Deployment Project Management

Machine Learning Tools Security Bash/Zsh, Python, MATLAB®, Julia, C++, R, IATEX

Docker, Kubernetes, AWS/GCP/Azure, HPCC (slurm, SGE), GitHub Actions

Jira, Confluence, git PyTorch/Lightning, Flux.jl

Jupyter/Pluto, SciPy/NumPy, matplotlib/seaborn, streamlit, SQL US citizen, SECRET clearance, interim TOP SECRET clearance

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

Oct 2021-Present Institution

SENIOR RESEARCH SCIENTIST

Clarifai Inc., Wilmington, DE

R&D for public sector AI/ML. Developed and optimized object detection, object tracking, and dataset enrichment algorithms using PyTorch, Docker, Kubernetes. Developed and deployed solutions on bare-metal and cloud compute. Technical lead on a multimillion dollar ARR line-of-effort as part of Project MAVEN for USDI/NGA. Competed against and outperformed trillion-dollar companies in head-to-head competition. Implemented unsupervised data preprocessing that improved state-of-the-art by up to 35% average precision on some classes. Presented at collaboration events and industry conferences. Onboarded, assigned and monitored work of senior and junior research staff. Maintained documentation on best practices/workflow for development.

Sep 2020-Sep 2021 Institution STAFF RESEARCH SCIENTIST

Boston Fusion Corp., Lexington, MA

R&D for public sector AI/ML. Developed rule-based AI and machine learning models for denoising radar, maritime surveillance, sensor fusion, and semantic classification. Successfully navigated SBIR projects to Phase III as technical lead. Primary author on SBIR/STTR proposals and scrum master.

Jul 2018-Aug 2020 Principal Investigator Institution Scientific Programmer & Data Analyst

Michael Hasselmo, DPHIL

Center for Systems Neuroscience, Boston University, Boston, MA

Designed and maintained software tools to study neuromodulation in the entorhinal cortex of rodents, including automating data analysis on high-performance computing hardware, designing statistical and numerical models, integrating state-of-the-art machine learning for motion tracking, and automating data collection in experiments using Arduino microcontrollers. Published three papers, two conference papers, and developed a tech stack still used by the lab today. Built and administrated the website. Enrolled in graduate courses concurrently through tuition remission.

 $\begin{array}{c} {\rm Feb~2015\text{-}Jul~2018} \\ Principal~Investigator \\ Institution \end{array}$ 

Research Assistant in Computational Neuroscience

Eve Marder,  $\operatorname{PhD}$ 

Brandeis University, Waltham, MA

Built simulation software for neuronal simulation, including xolot1, which simulates at state-of-the-art speeds with built-in parameter optimization and real-time visualization. Software and documentation design patterns developed for xolot1 have been adopted company-wide at Inscopix (VC-backed neurotech firm, \$20-25M ARR, acquired by Bruker Corp. in 2022). Studied neuromodulation using biophysically-realistic models of a motor circuit.

# EDUCATION

Jan 2021-Present PhD Student in Biomedical Engineering

InstitutionWorcester Polytechnic Institute, Worcester, MA

GPA: 4.0/4.0

Prof. Adam Lammert, PhD Advisor

Using compressive sensing and machine learning to dramatically reduce the number Research

of trials required to characterize high-dimensional representations of tinnitus in a

reverse correlation experiment.

Non-Degree Graduate Student in Engineering Aug 2018-Aug 2020

Boston University, Boston, MA Institution

GPA: 3.8/4.0

Courses Taken Linear Algebra, Statistical & Numerical Methods, Ordinary Differential Equations,

Partial Differential Equations, Machine Learning, Universal Natural Language

Processing, Artificial Intelligence.

May 2018Master of Science in Neuroscience

Brandeis University, Waltham MA Highest Honors, GPA: 3.4/4.0Institution

ThesisDifferential Responses to Neuromodulation in Model Neurons

 $of \ the \ Crustace an \ Stomatogastric \ Ganglion$ 

AdvisorProf. Eve Marder, PhD

May 2018 Bachelor of Science in Neuroscience

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN BIOLOGICAL PHYSICS

InstitutionBrandeis University, Waltham MA

Highest Honors, GPA: 3.4/4.0 Minor in the History of Ideas

AdvisorsProf. Eve Marder, PhD & Prof. Aparna Baskaran, PhD

#### Funding

Jan 2022 Tinnitus Characterization using Reverse Correlation with Applications to Retraining Therapies, Pilot Project Program, UMASS Center for Clinical and Translational Science (\$50,000)

Computational Neuroscience Traineeship, NIH/NIMH (\$11,000)

Mar 2017

Apr 2016 Quantitative Biology Research Community Fellowship,  ${\tt HHMI}$  (\$5,000)

#### Maintained Open-Source Projects

Dec 2022-Present Website

Publications

Tinnitus Reconstruction

https://alec-hoyland.github.io/tinnitus-reconstruction/

Hoyland, N. Barnett, et al. 2023; Hoyland, N. V. Barnett, et al. 2023

Reconstructs a frequency spectrum representation of the subjective internal experience of tinnitus, using human subject data from a brief alternate-forced choice task. The reconstruction algorithms are linear regression- and compressed sensing-

based.

Dec 2019-Present Website Neural Decoder

https://github.com/hasselmonians/neural-decoder

Produces a stochastic convolutional model of the relationship between an extrinsic

observative signal and an intrinsic covarying spike train.

Aug 2018-Present Publications

Website

BANDWIDTHESTIMATOR

Dannenberg, Lazaro, et al. 2020; Dannenberg, Kelley, et al. 2019

https://github.com/hasselmonians/BandwidthEstimator

Implements a maximum-likelihood leave-one-out cross-validated bandwidth parameter estimation algorithms for general point processes (including spike

trains).

Aug 2018-Present Publications Website RATCATCHER

Dannenberg, Lazaro, et al. 2020; Dannenberg, Kelley, et al. 2019

https://github.com/hasselmonians/RatCatcher

A data- & analysis-agnostic pipeline for automating analysis on a high-performance

computing cluster, with a local interface. Written in MATLAB®.

Aug 2017-Present Publications Website

Gorur-Shandilya, Hoyland, and Marder 2018; Hoyland 2018

https://go.brandeis.edu/xolotl

A fast and flexible neuronal simulator in C++ with an extensive MATLAB® front-end.

Achieves state-of-the-art efficiency on non-branching models.

# **PUBLICATIONS**

Hoyland, Alec, Nelson V. Barnett, Benjamin W. Roop, Danae Alexandrou, Myah Caplan,

Jacob Mills, Benjamin Parrell, Divya A. Chari, and Adam C. Lammert (2023).

"Reverse Correlation Uncovers More Complete Tinnitus Spectra".

In: IEEE Open Journal of Engineering in Medicine and Biology, pp. 1–3. ISSN: 2644-1276. DOI: 10.1109/0JEMB.2023.3275051.

Dannenberg, Holger, Hallie Lazaro, Pranav Nambiar, Alec Hoyland, and Michael E Hasselmo (Dec. 10, 2020). "Effects of Visual Inputs on Neural Dynamics for Coding of Location and

Running Speed in Medial Entorhinal Cortex".

In: eLife 9. Ed. by Adrien Peyrache, Laura L Colgin, and Kevin Allen, e62500. ISSN: 2050-084X. DOI: 10.7554/eLife.62500. URL: https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.62500 (visited on 06/06/2022).

Hasselmo, Michael E., Andrew S. Alexander, Alec Hoyland, Jennifer C. Robinson,

Marianne J. Bezaire, G. William Chapman, Ausra Saudargiene, Lucas C. Carstensen, and Holger Dannenberg (Apr. 8, 2020). "The Unexplored Territory of Neural Models: Potential Guides for Exploring the Function of Metabotropic Neuromodulation". In: Neuroscience. ISSN: 0306-4522.

DOI: 10.1016/j.neuroscience.2020.03.048.

URL: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0306452220302141 (visited on 06/25/2020).

Dannenberg, Holger, Craig Kelley, Alec Hoyland, Caitlin K. Monaghan, and Michael E. Hasselmo (May 1, 2019). "The Firing Rate Speed Code of Entorhinal Speed Cells Differs across Behaviorally Relevant Time Scales and Does Not Depend on Medial Septum Inputs".

In: Journal of Neuroscience 39.18, pp. 3434–3453. ISSN: 0270-6474, 1529-2401.

DOI: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1450-18.2019. pmid: 30804092.

URL: http://www.jneurosci.org/content/39/18/3434 (visited on 06/12/2019).

Gorur-Shandilya, Srinivas, Alec Hoyland, and Eve Marder (2018). "Xolotl: An Intuitive and Approachable Neuron and Network Simulator for Research and Teaching".

In: Frontiers in Neuroinformatics 12. ISSN: 1662-5196. DOI: 10.3389/fninf.2018.00087.

URL: https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fninf.2018.00087/full (visited on 06/01/2021).

Hoyland, Alec (2018). "Differential Responses to Neuromodulation in Model Neurons of the Crustacean Stomatogastric Ganglion". Thesis. Brandeis University.

URL: http://bir.brandeis.edu/handle/10192/35686 (visited on 08/14/2019).

#### Conference Papers & Posters

Hoyland, Alec, Nelson Barnett, Benjamin Roop, Danae Alexandrou, Benjamin Parrel, Divya Chari, and Adam Lammert (Feb. 11, 2023).

"Characterizing Complex Tinnitus Sounds Using Reverse Correlation: A Feasibility Study". In: Association for Research in Otolaryngology. 46th Annual Midwinter Meeting. Orlando FL.

Ning, Wing, John H. Bladon, Jerry Chen, S Steinwenter, Alec Hoyland, and Michael E. Hasselmo (2019). "A Cortical-Hippocampal Network Supporting the Temporal Organization of Memory". In: 2019 Neuroscience Meeting Planner. Society for Neuroscience. 164.05. Chicago, IL.

Dannenberg, Holger, Craig Kelley, Alec Hoyland, Caitlin K. Monaghan, and Michael E. Hasselmo (2018). "Speed Coding by Entorhinal Cortex Speed Cells Differs across Behaviorally Relevant Timescales and Is Independent of Cholinergic Modulation". In: Society for Neuroscience. 508.27. San Diego, CA.

# Teaching & Mentorship

Sep 2022-Dec 2022 Institution AI/ML SUBJECT MATTER EXPERT

Norfolk Collegiate School, Norfolk, VA

Presented on machine learning concepts to middle school students working on a LEGO robotics competition project. Built an interactive Streamlit demo of a fully-connected neural network for demonstration purposes.

 $\begin{array}{c} \hbox{Jul 2018-Aug 2020} \\ \hline \\ Institution \end{array}$ 

SCIENTIFIC COMPUTING TUTOR

Boston University, Boston, MA

Organized and ran a Julia learning group for undergraduate and graduate students.

Aug 2016-Aug 2018 Institution QUANTITATIVE BIOLOGY RESEARCH COMMUNITY (QBREC)

Brandeis University, Waltham, MA

QBReC is an interdisciplinary undergraduate research community for handpicked Brandeis science majors, who perform hands-on research internships. Engaged in this research and mentored other students as a co-leader.

Oct 2016-Oct 2018 Institution SPLASH TEACHING FELLOW

Brandeis University, Waltham, MA

Taught theoretical neuroscience courses to high-school students. Organized "lunch & learn" seminars between high school students and Brandeis faculty.

Oct 2014-Feb 2017 Institution Brandeis Maker Lab Volunteer

 ${\bf Brande is} \ {\bf University}, \ {\bf Waltham}, \ {\bf MA}$ 

Worked with the Brandeis Maker Lab's 3-D printers, volunteered at the student-run hackathon geared towards learning and hardware.

# REFERENCES

Position | SHELLEY CAZARES, PHD | Research Manager

Institution Clarifai Inc.
Phone 612-747-5740

Adam Lammert, PhD

Position | Assistant Professor of Biomedical Engineering (Computer Science affiliate)

Institution | Worcester Polytechnic Institute

Email | alammert@wpi.edu

Dan Marasco, PhD

Position | Machine Learning Researcher (formerly Research Manager)

Institution | Palantir Technologies (formerly Clarifai Inc.)

Phone 732-778-7760

Email daniel.eric.marasco@gmail.com

CARL WEIR, PHD

Position | Director of Cognitive Fusion

Institution Boston Fusion Phone 617-583-5730

Email | carl.weir@bostonfusion.com

BERNARD CHARTIER

Position | Principal Research Scientist

Institution Boston Fusion

Phone 617-583-5730

Email | bernard.chartier@bostonfusion.com

MICHAEL HASSELMO, DPHIL

Position | University Professor of Psychological & Brain Sciences

Institution Boston University
Phone 617-353-1397
Email hasselmo@bu.edu

•

Position | EVE MARDER, PhD | University Professor of Neuroscience

Institution Brandeis University
Phone 781-736-3140

Email | marder@brandeis.edu

Aparna Baskaran, PhD

Position | Associate Professor of Physics

Institution Brandeis University
Phone 781-736-2866

Email aparna@brandeis.edu

JIM LACKNER, PHD

Position | Professor of Physiology Institution | Brandeis University

Phone 781-736-2033

Email | lackner@brandeis.edu